<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>IX queries upon the printed charge of the army against the XI. members and the papers thereto annexed: submitted to the publike consideration of the Parliament, army, and all lovers of justice, truth, parliaments, and their native country.</title>
            <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91235</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4023</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E394_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201616</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862116</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862116</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114265</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91235)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114265)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 62:E394[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>IX queries upon the printed charge of the army against the XI. members and the papers thereto annexed: submitted to the publike consideration of the Parliament, army, and all lovers of justice, truth, parliaments, and their native country.</title>
                  <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Prynne by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Expulsion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114265:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114265:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IX
QVERIES
Upon the Printed
Charge of the Army
againſt the XI.</p>
            <p>MEMBERS
And the Papers thereto annexed: Submitted to the
Publike conſideration of the
PARLIAMENT,
ARMY,
And all Lovers of Juſtice, Truth, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,
and their Native COUNTRY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JER. 9. 4, 5.</bibl>
               <p>Take ye heed every one of his Neighbour, and truſt ye not in
any Brother; for each Brother will utterly ſupplant, and every Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
will walk with ſlanders. And they will deceive every man his
Neighbour, and will not ſpeak the Truth; they have taught their
tongues to ſpeak Lyes; and weary themſelves to commit Iniquity.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>LUKE 3. 14.</bibl>
               <p>And the Souldiers demanded of John, ſaying; And what
ſhall we do? And he ſaid unto them; Do violence to no man (or, put
no man in fear, <hi>much leſs a whole Parliament, City, Kingdome</hi>) neither
ACC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE ANY MAN FALSLY; and be content
with your wages.</p>
            </q>
            <p>London, Printed in the Year, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:114265:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114265:2"/>
            <head>Nine QUERIES upon the Printed
CHARGE of the Army againſt the
MEMBERS, and the Papers thereto
annexed: Submitted to the publick
Conſideration of the ARMY, and
all Lovers of Juſtice, Truth, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
and their native Country.</head>
            <p>1. BY what Law, Commiſſion or Authority, the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,
Officers and Soldiers</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> can <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi>
not only their <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>Declarations</hi> (of
dangerous conſequence), but their very <hi>Charge</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the <hi>Members of the Commons Houſe,</hi> to be <hi>printed</hi> and
publiſhed, without the <hi>Privity</hi> or <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Houſe?</hi> And
whether this be not an encroachment of a tranſcendent <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary
power</hi> (which themſelves condemn in others) and an
<hi>high Breach of the Houſes Priviledges;</hi> whereof the <hi>Houſe</hi>
and whole <hi>Kingdom</hi> (whom they repreſent) ought to be deeply
ſenſible, and have more juſt cauſe to complain againſt the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi>
then they againſt the <hi>accuſed Members?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Whether this Charge delivered into the Houſe againſt
theſe eminent Members, in the name of the <hi>whole Army</hi> (the
greateſt part whereof do neither know the <hi>perſons</hi> impeached,
much leſs their <hi>guiltineſs</hi> of the <hi>crimes</hi> whereof they accuſe
them; without the names of any particular perſons thereto
ſubſcribed undertaking to make good this charge at their utmoſt
peril, or elſe to ſuffer and make them and the Houſe full <hi>repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114265:3"/>
for their falſe <hi>Impeachment,</hi> be warrantable or receivable
by any <hi>Law of God,</hi> or of <hi>the Land,</hi> or former <hi>Preſidents;</hi> and
of a more <hi>arbitrary, dangerous</hi> and <hi>unjuſt</hi> conſtitution, and
direful conſequence, then any theſe new <hi>Pretenders to publick
Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Declaimers</hi> againſt <hi>Arbitrary power,</hi> complain of in
their <hi>Charge</hi> or <hi>Remonſtrances?</hi> and directly contrary to the
<note n="*" place="margin">See Raſtal Accuſation.</note> 
               <hi>Statutes</hi> of 25. <hi>E. 3. c. 4. 27. E. 3. c. 18. 38. E.</hi> 3.
<hi>c. 9. 17. R. 2. c. 6. 15. H. 6. c.</hi> 4. And whether this <hi>Charge,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
in by an whole <hi>mutinous Army,</hi> in their name alone, be
not expreſly made voyd and null by the Statute of 31. <hi>H. 6. c.</hi> 1.
concerning <hi>Jack Cade</hi> and his Rebellious popular Army;
which Enacts; <hi>That all Inditements</hi> (or Charges) <hi>and all
things depending thereof, had and made, under the Power and
Tyranny of</hi> Cade <hi>and his Army; during their Rebellion and
Inſurrection, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDER COLO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R OF J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE for
Reformation of the Laws (who gather the people together in great
number by falſe ſubtil imagined language) ſhal be voyd, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled,
repealed and holden for none:</hi> And that ALL IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DITEMENTS
(or Charges) IN TIME COMING IN
LIKE CASE, UNDER POVVER OF TYRANNY, RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>B<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>LLION
AND STIRRING HAD, SHAL BE OF NO
RECORD NOR EFFECT, BUT VOYD IN LAVV. And
ſo not to be received by the Parliament, till the Army be disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;
whoſe Proceedings, Remonſtrances, and Pretences now,
are very like that of <hi>Cades,</hi> and his party then; and may warn
the Parliament and <hi>London</hi> to ſtand upon their guard; and not
to let in the <hi>Army</hi> now, without reſiſtance, as they did then, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Speed. Chron. P. 849, 850. Grafion</hi> p. 610. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> 
               <hi>faire promiſes, and a prohibition of murder, rape or rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery
(which allured the hearts of the common people):</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
being let in, they apprehended and beheaded the Lord <hi>Say,</hi>
Treaſurer of England, <hi>James Cromer</hi> his ſon in law and others,
and rifled or fined divers of the Aldermen and other Citizens, and
threatned the reſt; who at laſt repenting of their folly, when it
was almoſt to late, for the preſervation of their lives and goods,
raiſed and drew in forces; expulſed <hi>Cade,</hi> with his ungra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
company; and by that means diſſipated his tumultuous
Army: A ſtory worthy both the Parliaments, Cities and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
preſent conſideration.</p>
            <p>3. Whether a general Charge in ambiguous Terms againſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114265:3"/>
               <hi>XI.</hi> eminent <hi>Members</hi> at once (moſt of which have not only
ſuffered, but done gallant ſervice in the field for the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Peoples Liberties</hi>) in general, ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
and uncertain terms, without deſcending to particulars of
fact, perſons, time, place, or other circumſtance, to which by Law
they are bound to anſwer, and cannot poſſibly make defence; and
their not determining or ſpecifying which of them are guilty of
all the Charge, which only of one or more (themſelves confeſſing
that <hi>ſome of them are</hi> only <hi>guilty of one Head,</hi> in the ſame paper)
be not a moſt illegal, injurious, arbitrary Accuſation and
Proceeding, contrary to all Rules of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity;</hi> and a
greater invading, infringing, and endeavoring to overturn the
<hi>Rights and Liberties of the Subjects of this Kingdom</hi> (and of
Parliaments too) <hi>in arbitrary, violent and oppreſſive ways,</hi>
then any chargeable againſt all or any of the <hi>XI.</hi> Members in the
firſt Article? which they may now juſtly recharge againſt the
<hi>Army,</hi> by way of recrimination, whoſe <hi>Proceedings</hi> give the
<hi>Lye</hi> to their <hi>Pretences,</hi> as the<note n="*" place="margin">See Maſter <hi>Rheymes</hi> his Narration.</note> 
               <hi>King</hi> himſelf hath done to ſome
of their <hi>Declarations,</hi> touching his willingneſs to remove from
<hi>Holdenby;</hi> and this very Charge doth too: which makes no
mention of any <hi>Plot or Conspiracy</hi> by theſe <hi>Members</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
the <hi>King</hi> from <hi>Holdenby,</hi> &amp;c. Or of <hi>Joyce</hi> his pretences
why his perſon was ſeized by the <hi>Army:</hi> which hereby appears
to be a meer <hi>figment</hi> and unjuſt <hi>pretext,</hi> to colour that <hi>Treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
Action;</hi> and make wiſe men ſuſpect, their other fair pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals
to the Parliament for <hi>Peace and publick Juſtice</hi> (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted
by ſubſequent Proceedings) are meer Fictions too, to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
ſome worſe deſignes without oppoſition.</p>
            <p>4, With what colour or ſhadow of Religion, Iuſtice or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
can an Army, profeſſing and ſtiling themſelves <hi>Saints,</hi>
grow ſo unchriſtianly impatient, outragious, and unlike their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
as upon a pretence of ſome falſ informations, miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
&amp; ſcandalous ſuggeſtions made againſt them to the Houſe,
concerning a Petition, &amp; engaging the Houſe by ſurpriſe to paſs a
Vote againſt them, ſince recalled; in ſtead of paſſing by, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
and putting up ſuch an injury (after competent ſatisfaction)
to fal <hi>into ſuch diſtempers, as to be diſobliged and diſcouraged
from any further ingagement in the Parliaments ſervice or Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands
preſervation,</hi> (as they unchriſtianly and ungratefully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
in their 2, 3, &amp; 4. Articles of Charge) and in ſtead
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114265:4"/>
thereof to march up againſt the Parliament, ſeize the King; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach
Members; demand all arrears before disbanding, endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
the Parliament, Kingdom; ſcandalize Religion, rejoyce
Malignants, ſad the hearts of all good men; and forfeit their
own honor and reputation, though better payd, rewarded, and
dealt with by the Parliament, and leſs injured then any other
Armies, Officers, Soldiers, imployed by them, who never manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
ſuch high contemptuous carriages againſt the Houſes though
never ſo deboyſt or irreligious: Is this Conſcience? this Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?
this your piety, and humility, after all your experiences of
Gods preſence? Is God with you, or before your eyes in ſuch
impatience or miſcarriages? Or is M. <hi>Peters</hi> with you to mind you
of what he <hi>oft proteſted</hi> in the Pulpit in your names, <hi>Your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs
to lay down your Necks, Lives, and to live under Rocks
and Caves in America, rather then not to diſband at the leaſt
intimation of the Parliament, or to do any act impeaching
their priviledges or proceedings?</hi> And was he then, or wil ye
preſume now to make him a <hi>Lyar,</hi> to blaſt your own and his
reputation with God &amp; men? Conſider this in cold blood when
you are upon your beds, and deſiſt with remorſe and ſhame from
ſuch unchriſtian ways and tumults, which wil render you more
odious and execrable then the Gunpowder-Traytors, and ſet all
mens hearts, hands, tongues againſt you.</p>
            <p>5. Whether the Army by ſuch general and uncertain Charges
as theſe might not impeach the whole Houſe it ſelf, as wel as
theſe <hi>XI.</hi> Members? Whether their demand, <hi>that the
Houſe ſhould forthwith ſuſpend them,</hi> without the leaſt ſhadow
of proof upon ſuch an illegal charge to which no certain anſwer
can be made, be not an equalling, juſtifying and exceeding the
Kings and his armed parties demands againſt the five Members
only upon more particular Articles then theſe; which ſeem at firſt
a meer plot to take away their Votes for the preſent (&amp; after that
the Votes of others both in Houſes reſerved for a future liſt) that
their Independent party only may ſway &amp; Vote what they pleaſe
in both; and their Officers in the Army that are Members<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be both
parties, accuſers, witneſſes and judges againſt theſe now accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
contrary to all Law and Juſtice, and ſo they wil be ſure to
ſuffer what ever their innocency be? or wil not the Army be more
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114265:4"/>
incenſed with their juſt acquittal, which wil much redound to
diſhonor and heighten their diſcontents? And wil not this be arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
and tyrannical Iuſtice in the ſuperlative degree?</p>
            <p>6. Whether the <hi>Armies</hi> ſilence in not propounding their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
demands for juſtice in their own and peoples behalf, or not
impeaching any of the accuſed members, til they were voted to
<hi>diſband,</hi> or go for <hi>Ireland;</hi> and their charge againſt them in
their 2. 3. and 4. Articles, <hi>to break the Army,</hi> and <hi>pul it in
peices,</hi> by authority of Parliament (when there was no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
uſe of its ſervice here,) amounting in plain Engliſh to no
more; but that they endeavoured and cauſed the Houſes to
vote the Armies disbanding, and ſend ſome of them into <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
under Major <hi>General Skippons</hi> and <hi>Maſſyes</hi> commands,
(which no rational man can deem a crime, the war being ended
and the people eaten out with <hi>Taxes</hi> and <hi>freequartring</hi> of the
Army, and <hi>Ireland</hi> in diſtreſs) be nor a clear demonſtration to
all the world; that this charge againſt the members, and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel
againſt the Houſes votes, is but a meer pretence to keep the
<hi>Army</hi> from disbanding; til they have by its overawing power
brought other deſigns to paſs both in the Parliament, City,
kingdom? one whereof is clearly intimated in their <hi>charge</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Papers;</hi> namely to ſuſpend &amp; throw out of the Houſe <hi>all old,</hi>
and new <hi>elected members</hi> (how duly ſoever choſen or returned)
who are not of their party, or likely to oppoſe their Projects, to
fil up their places with <hi>New members</hi> of their own <hi>godly party;</hi>
and to diſpoſe of all places of Power and <hi>Judicature, to mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi>
of their own: (and then to effect what changes they
pleaſe in Church and ſtate) as their exceptions againſt theſe
eminent Members, their deſire actually <hi>to ſuſpend them the
Houſe,</hi> upon this <hi>general, uncertain, frivolous Charge,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
any the leaſt proof or Conviction; their exception to the
Elections in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> (though all very faire) <hi>Wales,</hi> and
<hi>elſewhere;</hi> and their indirect forcible practiſes to bring in <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
and Officers</hi> of their own in all places, when this <hi>Army</hi> or
their party had any power (of which there are many ſad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints)
with their exceptions to <hi>the Parliaments Judges,</hi> unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably
demonſtrate to the eye of all the world, beſides other
particulars, which may ſhortly ſee the light, with many late
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114265:5"/>
printed Pamphlets (eſpecially <hi>Englands Birthright,</hi>) and
their late <hi>Propoſitions</hi> concerning the <hi>Change of Parliament
Members</hi> &amp;c. and Coronet <hi>Joyce</hi> his printed Relation, which
accuſeth <hi>two other Members</hi> not mentioned to this liſt, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
with many others of both Houſes for a ſecond) which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
the ſame. A deſign ſo dangerous and deſtructive, as may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken
the Parliament, &amp; all honeſt men in time to endeavour its
prevention, which without Gods mercy and their utmoſt activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
is elſe unavoydably like to fall upon us in a moment.</p>
            <p>7. Whether the <hi>Armies</hi> refuſal to disband or march more
remote from <hi>London</hi> according to the <hi>Houſes Votes;</hi> their
ſurpriſing and removing the <hi>Kings Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Commiſſioners</hi>
of both <hi>Houſes</hi> againſt <hi>their wils</hi> and Proteſtations, upon falſe
pretences without and againſt the Parliaments privity; their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving
the Artillery from <hi>Oxford</hi> (throwing up their hats and
crying out, <hi>hay for London</hi> &amp;c. as they marched thence;) and
advancing ſo near to <hi>London,</hi> as to ſeaze upon moſt paſſages
near it, ſearch many paſſengers repairing to it, and threatning
to march up even to the Parliaments doors, (to which they
make neerer approaches every day) in a tumultuous, violent
and warlike manner, to impeach, affright and aſſault the
Members of Parliament, in or near the Houſes, and by violence
outrage and threats, to awe and incenſe the Parliament to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
<hi>their Votes, ſuſpend their Members,</hi> grant them all their
unreaſonable demands before any expreſſions of their obedience
to them, and to impoſe what conditions they pleaſe upon them;
with their Letters and Remonſtrances to the City and people
to engage them againſt, and diſingage them from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to ſide with them, (in ſome whereof they court <hi>the very
Malignants once in arms,</hi> complaining of the <hi>breach of Articles</hi>
and craving <hi>reparation for their wrongs</hi> &amp;c.) their ſeiſing of <hi>Col.
Birch</hi> a member, and removing his and other forces ſent for <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi>
relief, &amp;c. ought not more juſtly to be charged againſt ſome
<hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> in the Army (who have moſt appeared in
theſe mutinous ways) by the accuſed Members, their Officers,
Commanders, both Houſes and the Kingdom, (being ſtil perſiſted
in) then the Officers and Armies may or can charge the <hi>accuſed
Members</hi> for <hi>inviting, encouraging, abetting, or Countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,
divers Reformadoes and other Officers and Souldiers tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuouſly,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114265:5"/>
and violently</hi> to gather together at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>
to affright <hi>and aſſault the Members</hi> &amp;c. As they do in their
<hi>fift Article:</hi> which tumult was ſoon quieted; and being an
Injury only to the Houſe not Army, ſince the tumults in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
and no ways relating to the Army (who ſtil act the ſame
themſelves or worſe which they thus heavily Charge on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers)
is a very forraign Charge with reference to the Members;
and no other (by an over-ruling divine hand of providence) but
a Charge and Impeachment againſt themſelves by way of juſt
recrimination; for which they ought to yeeld up their Officers
and principal Mutiners to the Parliaments and Kingdoms
Iuſtice, by the ſame Law (and far more equity) as they demand
the Members In which regard that divine text (aptly chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cterizing
theſe Accuſers) may juſtly be applyed to them, <hi>Rom.</hi>
2. 17. &amp;c. <hi>Behold thou makeſt thy boaſt of God; and art con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident,
that thou thy ſelf art a guide to the bl<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd a light to them
which are in darkneſs, &amp;c. Thou therefore that teacheſt</hi> (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peacheſt)
<hi>another, teacheſt</hi> (impeacheſt) <hi>thou not thy ſelf?</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>Thou that makeſt thy boaſt of the Law; through breaking the
Law</hi> (yea Priviledges of Parliament in an higher degree then
thoſe thou accuſeſt) <hi>diſhonoreſt thou God? For the name of
God is blaſphemed omong the Gentiles</hi> (among Papiſts, Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,
Prelatical, prophane and carnal perſons) <hi>through you,</hi> by
theſe your Antiparliamentary and Mutinous Proceedings, which
have opened their months wide againſt you, and made them to
upbraid the Parliament and your deareſt Friends with this taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
language, to the very piercing of their ſouls: <hi>Lo theſe are
Your Saints, Your Religious godly Party, and Army; Your
Saviours and Protectors, who now riſe up in arms againſt you
to ruin the Parliament &amp; Kingdom, and trample on you at their
pleaſure?</hi> Did ever the prophaneſt Officers or Soldiers under
deceaſed <hi>Eſſex, Waller, Maſſey, Mancheſter,</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Comander requite &amp; uſe you thus, though more provoked
by ſome <hi>Independents of the Houſ with il language, caſheering,
jealouſies, falſe aſperſions and want of pay, then theſe devout
and mortified Saints? &amp;c.</hi> O conſider now at laſt of theſe true
<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s! and ſay with the Poet, <hi>Pudet haec opprobria Nobis &amp;
dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potmiſſe refelli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114265:6"/>
8. With what coulor of Conſcience, Modeſty or Juſtice can
the <hi>Army</hi> demand of the Parliament, not only <hi>one moneths pay</hi>
(though many of them have been lately liſted ſince the wars
without the Houſes privity, and therefore can in Juſtice claim
no wages from them) when they ſtand in ſuch high <hi>terms</hi> of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi>
and breach of their <hi>Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Authority;</hi> but to
receive <hi>equal pay with thoſe who obey their commands in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding
and lifting themſelves for Ireland?</hi> or that <hi>they ſhal
have no more Areares payd them, til the reſt be payd their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reares?</hi>
and that <hi>pending the debates and tranſactions betwixt
the Parliament and the Army, the Parliament would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
any new forces to be rayſed within this Kingdom, for their
own defence?</hi> when as themſelves without any order have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruted
the Army, made new <hi>praparation for war,</hi> and block
up <hi>London</hi> more and more dayly; as if they intended a <hi>new war</hi>
againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>City;</hi> and yet prohibit them to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
themſelves,</hi> that ſo they may at their pleaſure, (if they
grant them not all their unreaſonable (if not <hi>endleſs demands,</hi>
now every day multiplyed) ſurpriſe and pillage them at their
pleaſures, as the<note n="*" place="margin">Sleidan. <hi>Com l.</hi> 10. Chytraeus. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrand.</note> 
               <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> did the City and
Magiſtrates of <hi>Munſter</hi> under a <hi>pretence of peace, contrary to
their faith, to the Prince, City and Country,</hi> as <hi>ſoon as by
their fair promiſes, they had perſwaded them to retire home and
lay down their armes;</hi> whoſe extraordinary ſufferings for ſuch
over-credulus folly ſhould teach the Parliament and City wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
now to ſtand upon their guard, and not to expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves
to the mercy of a boiſterous diſcontented Army whoſe
demands grow higher every day; and tend only to engage all
others to their party, and diſingage them from the Parliament;
whoſe priviledges they pretend to ſupport, whiles they thus
infringe them, formerly refuſing to have the ſolemn league
and Covenant impoſed on them: which would have enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
them, (as wel as others) <hi>with ſincerity, reality and
CONSTANCY, to endeavour with their eſtates and lives
to preſerve the rights and priviledges of the Parliament; and
not ſuffer themſelves directly or indirectly by whatſoever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination,
perſwaſion or terror, to be divided or withdrawn from
this Covenant,</hi> &amp;c. which how wel ſome members of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114265:6"/>
Houſe and Army with oth<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> who have <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form,
let their own con<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, the would, and that <hi>high God</hi> to
whom they <hi>have lifted up their</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, when they ſolemnly
ſwore this Covenant, judge; and either excite them to a ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous
and real performance of it, or require the woful breach
of it at their perjured hands.</p>
            <p>9. whether any motions of the Army to the Parliament
ought to be heard or granted by the rules of juſtice, whilſt
they continue in contempt againſt it? Whether an Army who
profeſs this to be their principle, <hi>that no mans judgment or
conſcience ought to be forced, by any external violence, but
left free;</hi> can by any coulor of juſtice or conſcience, endeavour
to enforce by menaces or violence, the <hi>judgment,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
of the whole Parliament, whoſe <hi>Rights, Priviledges</hi>
and <hi>freedom</hi> they are bound in duty, and raiſed to <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>?
Whether every member of the Houſes, who though ſordid
fear of any humane power, or compli<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncy with the Army,
ſhal deſert or betray the freedom, <hi>Rights and Priviledges</hi>
of the Parliament, which himſelf hath <hi>ſolemnly ſworn, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted,
and ingaged to maintain, to the uttermoſt, with his
life and eſtate</hi> &amp;c. Ought not in juſtice to be thruſt out of
the Houſe by his fellow Members with contempt and ſcorn,
as unworthy ever to ſet there more, and a moſt treacherous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured
perſon, betraying his truſt to Parliament and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom?
And whether all members ought not in their greateſt exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies,
rather chearfully to lay down their lives, then the Houſes
freedom, Rights and Priviledges (wherewith the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
hath intruſted them, for the preſent Common good, and
ought to be intirely preſented and tranſmitted to poſterity for
the kingdoms future ſafety) infringed? And to take up <hi>Davids</hi>
magnanimous reſolution in their preſent ſtraits: <hi>Pſa.</hi> 3. 6. &amp; 27.
1, 3. <hi>I wil not be afraid of ten thouſands of people who have
ſet themſelves againſt me round about. Though an hoſt
ſhould encamp againſt me; my heart ſhal not fear: though
war ſhould riſe up againſt me, in this wil I be confident. The
Lord is my light, and my ſalvation, whom ſhal I fear?
the Lord is the ſtrength of my life, of whom ſhal I be afraid?</hi>
That member who cannot raiſe up his ſpirit in the worſt of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114265:7"/>
magnanimous reſolution in their preſent ſtraits: <hi>Pſa.</hi> 3. 6, &amp; 27.
1, 3. <hi>I wil not be afraid of ten thouſands of people who have
ſet themſelves againſt me round about. Though an hoſt
ſhould encamp againſt me; my heart ſhal not fear: though
war ſhould riſe up againſt me, in this wil I be confident. The
Lord is my light, and my ſalvation, whom ſhal I fear?
the Lord is the ſtrength of my life, of whom ſhal I be afraid?</hi>
That member who cannot raiſe up his ſpirit in the worſt of
times to ſuch an heroick Chriſtian Reſolution, preferring his
own perſonal ſafety, life or wealth before his Countries, is ſcarce
worthy ever to enter more within the Houſes doors; and that
true-bred <hi>Engliſhman</hi> unworthy to live, who wil not die at
he Houſes feet in maintaining of their juſt Freedom, Rights, and
Liberties, though in ſome things they may have formerly failed
in their duties; ſince if Parliaments be once trampled upon
and made contemptible by any (eſpecially by that Army which
was raiſed by them, and hath hitherto fought for their defence,
or any freinds to Parliaments) the Kingdom and people (who have
ſubſiſted by Parliaments) wil be eternally loſt and ruined. Which
ingaged both City &amp; Kingdom to adhere ſo faſt to the Parliament
againſt the King and his Cavaliers heretofore, whom they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
in Juſtice or honor now deſert, without infinite ingratitude,
ſcandal and diſgrace, nor any officers or ſouldiers in the Army o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly
oppoſe or enforce without this guilt of Treaſon and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion;
the breach of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1, 2, 3. and condemnation
of all their former faithful ſervices for its defence.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114265:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
